<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Autism on Nathan Mietkiewicz</title>
    <link>/tags/autism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Autism on Nathan Mietkiewicz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Nathan Mietkiewicz</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/autism/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated Measurement of Language Outcomes for Neurodevelopmental Disorders - NIDCD R01</title>
      <link>/project/language-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/language-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Improving spoken language use (i.e., discourse skills) is a common treatment goal for children with neurodevelopmental disorders, particularly for those with difficulties in conversational reciprocity, perseverative speech, or idiosyncratic/stereotyped word use. These features are clinically meaningful, and in previous projects, we have successfully applied Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods to measure these discourse skills using natural language samples from children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). However, while NLP methods yield diagnostically relevant measures, it is not known if they can be translated into meaningful outcome measures. To take this next step, important questions must be addressed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How stable and responsive are NLP discourse measures over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How consistent are the measures across different measurement contexts and lengths?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is their validity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what degree are measures impacted by general language or intellectual abilities?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of knowledge about these psychometric properties of NLP discourse measures is a problem because, without it, the likelihood that children’s use of spoken language can be targeted and impacted in large-scale clinical trials is remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long-term goal of this project is to harness the benefits of NLP to impact functional spoken language outcomes for children with neurodevelopmental disorders. The parent project (R01DC012033: “Computational Characterization of Language Use in Autism Spectrum Disorder”) took the first steps towards this goal by developing NLP algorithms to measure discourse skills based on raw (i.e., not coded or annotated) transcripts. Our strong results indicate difficulties in conversational reciprocity as well as elevated repetitive language behaviors among children with ASD compared to children without ASD, and were not due to differences in age, IQ, or language abilities. Our objective in this project is to take the next step to evaluate the suitability of these NLP automated discourse measures (ADMs) as outcomes for individuals with a range of intellectual abilities and diagnoses. Our approach will focus on optimizing stability of such measures, and assessing responsiveness to change over time, consistency across sampling contexts and sample lengths, and validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-modal Autism Phenotype Snapshot (MAPS): Automated measurement of outcomes for children with autism</title>
      <link>/project/maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/maps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Targeting core symptoms of Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) is a key treatment goal for parents of children with ASD. While many efficacious treatments for ASD have been developed, a major obstacle in evaluating these treatments among children with ASD has been the lack of adequate outcome measures (Anagnostou et al., 2014; Bolte &amp;amp; Diehl, 2013; Kanne et al., 2014). Most treatment studies have relied on informant-based measures (i.e., parent or clinician report) that either place a high burden on families, or require significant training and time to administer. Moreover, measures are often re-purposed from existing measures intended for screening or diagnosis, and do not provide continuous measures of symptoms that are responsive to change. Thus, there is a clear need to develop ASD outcome measures that are reliable, valid, and sensitive to change. In the absence of such outcome measures, our understanding of the efficacy of treatments for ASD will continue to be limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, automated methods for quantifying behavior have become more advanced, less intrusive, and more cost-effective, and could provide reliable and sensitive measures of behavioral change. However, these methods have yet to be translated into a viable outcome measure for use in treatment studies. For example, recent research has shown that autism symptoms can be objectively measured with automated methods such as eye-tracking (Rice, Moriuchi, Jones, &amp;amp; Klin, 2012), natural language processing (Gorman et al., 2016; Rouhizadeh et al., 2014; van Santen, Sproat, &amp;amp; Hill, 2013), and quantitative facial emotion analysis (Metallinou, Grossman, &amp;amp; Narayanan, 2013), and that such measures are interpretable and meaningful for the everyday lives of children and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to develop and validate a novel objective measurement tool, the Multi-modal Autism Phenotype Snapshot (MAPS), for use in clinical trials targeting core symptoms of autism. MAPS uses automated methods to measure autism-relevant behaviors across multiple modalities (gaze-tracking, natural language processing, facial expression analysis) while children watch and respond to audiovisual stimuli presented on a laptop. This project was funded by a Catalyst Award from the Oregon Clinical &amp;amp; Translational Research Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Characterization of Language Use in Females and Males with Autism Spectrum Disorder</title>
      <link>/project/sex-diffs-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sex-diffs-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The female clinical presentation of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is not well understood, and is a contributing factor to underidentification and delays in the diagnosis of ASDs among females, particularly for those who are verbal and without cognitive impairments. Sex differences in clinical presentation may make it more difficult to recognize ASD symptoms in females, yet evidence for differences between females and males in the two core symptom domains—social communication/interaction and repetitive behaviors and restricted interests—has been inconsistent. Although some studies have found stronger social communication/interaction skills in affected females than in males, researchers and clinicians have cautioned that these strengths may be superficial and allow females to “mask” their ASD symptoms, further contributing to underidentification among females. Similarly, restricted and repetitive behaviors may be less common among females with ASD, or they may simply look different from clinical expectations based on male presentations, again allowing females to “fly under the radar.” Thus, there is a critical need to further understanding of sex differences in the fundamental patterns of behavioral and social functioning relevant to the clinical presentation of ASD. In the absence of such knowledge, females with ASD will continue to be underidentified; affected females will be identified at older ages and thus will fail to benefit from access to early intervention services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long-term goal of this project is to further understanding of the female clinical presentation of ASD, so that improved methods for identification, assessment, and treatment of females with communication difficulties such as ASD can be developed. Our objective is to identify features that characterize atypical language use—a core symptom of ASD—among females with ASD. In the parent R01, we have developed and validated new Natural Language Processing based methods that automatically measure features of atypical language use based on raw (i.e., not coded) transcripts of natural language samples. Our strong preliminary data indicate significant impairments in conversational reciprocity and repetitive speech behaviors among children with ASD. For this administrative supplement, we propose to increase sample size of females with ASD in order to increase statistical power to analyze sex differences among children with ASD in atypical language use. Our rationale for this project is that successful identification of observable and objective differences (and similarities) between females and males in atypical language use would allow clinicians to better recognize, assess, and potentially treat symptoms of ASD in females.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
